Guide to the Steel/City Production Records, 1974-1977 CTC.1992.02
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Steel/City Production Records
1983-1992
ULS Archives & Special Collections
CTC.1992.02
3 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
Steel/City was a University of Pittsburgh documentary theater production written for the Bicentennial in 1976, portraying the social and industrial history of Pittsburgh. This collection contains records from the development and production of the play and the audio cassettes of the post-play discussions and town meetings.
Related Material
University of Pittsburgh Theatre Arts Department Records, 1960-1986, CTC.1974.02, Curtis Theatre Collection, Archives & Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh Library System
History
Steel/City was conceived and written by University of Pittsburgh Department of Theatre Arts professors Gil Elvgren and Attillio Favorini in the mid 1970's as part of the city's (and nation's) Bicentennial activities planned for 1976. Working from a concept of documentary theater with strong social relevance to the community, Steel/City's script was entirely composed of words actually spoken by real individuals. None of the dialog was created by the authors. In addition to extensive research on the history of Pittsburgh, its magnates and distant past, the authors also utilized oral history interviews conducted with retired steel workers and their families at the time the play was being composed. Their reminiscences were used to provide the dialog for Act III of the play, which takes place at a pensioners' picnic.
Steel/City was produced by the University of Pittsburgh Department of Theatre Arts in the spring and summer of 1976. It toured the region, and also was performed at the Smithsonian Institution's American Folklife Festival. In keeping with the authors' goal of relevance to the community, the audience was given the opportunity to discuss the play and the issues that it raised in several discussion sessions. These ranged from informal discussion groups held immediately after the performances, to more structured "town meetings" with a panel of local authorities on hand.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into three series:
Series I. Production Files
Series II. Research Files
Series III. Audio Cassettes
Scope and Content Notes
This collection consists of materials directly related to the production of the play, including grant applications, budget reports and scripts, as well as material generated during the process of research for the play. This includes photos, information on Pittsburgh and its steel industry history, oral interviews, etc. These materials are grouped by topic. Also included are recordings of the post-play discussion sessions and town meetings.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These records were gift of Attillio Favorini in 1992.
Previous Citation
Steel/City Production Records, 1974-1977, CTC.1992.02, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
"Steel/City" Production Records, 1974-1977, CTC.31, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- History -- Drama; Performing arts -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Steel industry and trade -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- History -- Drama; Theater; Elvgren, Gillette; Favorini, Attilio, 1943-; University of Pittsburgh. Department of Speech and Theatre Arts
- Production Files, I.
  Scope and Contents note
  Materials directly related to the production of the play. Incudes grant applications, budget reports, scripts.
  - American Revolution Bicentennial Administration grant request (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Audience survey (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Audience notes (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Barge productions (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cast lists (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence - Budget (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence - Cast (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence - City of Pittsburgh Bicentennial Committee (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence - Pennsylvania Bicentennial Commission (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence - Public relations (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence - United Steel Workers (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Documentary theater background (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Documentary theater sample script: "Bread and Roses" (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Essays (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Fact sheets (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Financial reports (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Grants and awards (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Individual or corporate contributors (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Meeting minutes (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Mini-festival (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Oral history projects (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "Pittsburgh, Ho!" project (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Polish Hill controversy (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Press releases (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Proposals (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Public Committee on the Humanities grant (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Reviews (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Scene research development - Andrew Carnegie (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Scene research development - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Smithsonian American Folklife Festival (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Steel/City scripts (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Teaching packet (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Testimonials (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Touring script (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Town meetings (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Research Files, II.
  These materials were generated during the research process for the play. They includes photos, information on Pittsburgh and it's steel industry history, oral interviews, etc. The materials are sub-divided by topic.
  - Labor, 1.
    - 12 hour day (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Strike, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Strike, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
    - 1930s mill towns (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 1930s union struggles (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Strike, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 1970s No Strike agreements (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Grievance handling (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Union newspapers (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Union speeches (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Voice of Labor pamphlet (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous, 2.
    - Oral History interviews (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Pittsburgh - Facts and figures, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Pittsburgh - Letters to the editor, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Research photos - 4x5 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Research photos - 8x10 (Box 3, Folder 17-18)
  - Society, 3.
    - Depression (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Ethnological research (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Industrial philosophies (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Immigration (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Poles (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Song research, 4.
    - Minstrel songs (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Union songs (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Steel, 5.
    - African-American steelworkers (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Carnegie Steel Co. newsletter (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Child labor (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Mill towns (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Post WWII (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Technical information (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Unemploymemt (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - U.S. Steel Corp. history (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - WWII production (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Wages (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Women in steel (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Work accidents (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Audio Cassettes, III.
  Recordings of the post-play discussion sessions and town meetings.
  - Post-play discussions, July 8 - August 5, 1976 (Box 5)
  - Post-play discussions and town meetings, July 18 - August 15, 1976 (Box 6)